Guide to the Norman D. Anderson Collection on Ferris Wheels and Related Materials
Norman D. Anderson Collection on Ferris Wheels and Related Materials
- Research Files of Norman D. Anderson
  - Ferris Wheels and Amusement Rides, Miscellaneous, including some patents
    - British Patents, 1890s-1980s (Legalbox 21, Folder 5)
    - Exposition/Fairs Bibliographic Materials, 1930s-1990s (Legalbox 22, Folder 5)
    - Ferris Wheels, Additional Materials, 1890s-1980s (Legalbox 20, Folder 15)
    - Ferris Wheels, Miscellaneous, varied, primarily 20th century (Legalbox 26, Folder 10)
    - Ferris Wheel Toys, 1980s-2000s (Legalbox 22, Folder 1)
    - Ferris Wheel Collectibles, 1980s-1990s (Legalbox 21, Folder 7)
    - Minority Parks, primarily 1930s (Legalbox 22, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings and Photocopies, 1930s-2000s (Legalbox 21, Folder 6)
  - Patents
    - United States Patents, Ferris Wheels: 1,000,000-2,000,000, 1880s-1910 (Legalbox 27, Folder 3)
    - United States Patents, Ferris Wheels: 2,000,000-2,999,999, 1930s-1950s (Legalbox 27, Folder 4)
    - United States Patents, Ferris Wheels and Amusement Rides, 1890-1960 (Legalbox 27, Folder 5)
    - Questions and Answers About Patents, 1982 (Legalbox 27, Folder 6)
    - United States Patents, Ferris Wheels and Amusement Devices, 1890 (Legalbox 27, Folder 7)
    - United States Patents, 1870s-1910s (Legalbox 27, Folder 9)
      Original folder labeled, "to the office ND anderson 356 Pope"
    - United States Patents, 1880s-1910 (Legalbox 27, Folder 8)
      These patents pertain to Ferris Wheels and other amusement park rides. They appear to be part of the research compiled for Dr. Anderson's book Amusement Rides and Devices: A Compilation of United States Patents. (Published 1989)
    - Patents, Ferris Wheels, Patent Work (Includes patents from 1880s-1920s) (Legalbox 27, Folder 10)
    - Patents, Ferris Wheels, Duplicate Work (pulled for Appendix B), 1890s-1980s (Legalbox 27, Folder 11)
      This material appears to be information (mostly United States Patents) pulled for Appendix B of Dr. Anderson's Amusement Rides and Devices. This information also includes an edited index from the aforementioned text.
    - Patents, Ferris Wheels, United States and England, 1890s-1930s (Legalbox 27, Folder 12)
    - Patents, Second Edition, Patents and Related Information, 1890s-1920s, approximately (Legalbox 26, Folder 13)
    - Patents, Second Edition, United States Patents, Ferris Wheels, 3,000,001-Design Patents (Legalbox 27, Folder 1)
    - Patents, Second Edition, More Patents, 1890s-1910s (Legalbox 27, Folder 2)
    - Foreign Patents, primarily United Kingdom, 1880s-1980s (Legalbox 28, Folder 1)
      These materials also include material pertaining to Paul Braithwaite's work, including a publication entitled Roundabout Patents and corrections and additions to this publication.
      Braithwaite Paul
- Photographs and Images
  Though photographs and images are located throughout the Research Files, this series is comprised mostly of photographs and images used in Dr. Norman Anderson's books. These include several juvenile science books as well as Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History. The images may span centuries in origin, but the dates given are the dates relevant to the publication of the book.
  - Images Used in Science Books by Norman D. Anderson
    These images were used in Dr. Anderson's publications: Halley's CometandFireworks! Pyrotechnics on Display. Both books are juvenile educational texts.
    - Images from Halley's Comet by Norman Anderson, 1970s-1980s (Legalbox 28, Folder 6)
      These images were used in a juvenile nonfiction book entitled Halley's Comet by Norman D. Anderson and Walter R. Brown.
    - Photographs from Fireworks!: Pyrotechnics on Display by Norman D. Anderson and Walter R. Brown, 1980s (Legalbox 28, Folder 9)
    - Negatives from Fireworks!: Pyrotechnics on Display by Norman D. Anderson and Walter R. Brown, 1980s (Legalbox 28, Folder 10)
  - Images Used in Raleigh: North Carolina 's Capital City on Postcards by Norman D. Anderson and B.T. Fowler, 1990s
    - Photographs of Postcards from Raleigh: North Carolina's Capital City on Postcards, Folder 1 (Legalbox 28, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Postcards from Raleigh: North Carolina's Capital City on Postcards, Folder 2 (Legalbox 28, Folder 8)
  - Photographs and Images used in Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, 1980s-1990s
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter One, Early Ferris Wheels, 17th century-1940s (Legalbox 28, Folder 3)
      The date ranges of this material are extensive, though all images pertain to early Ferris wheels and many are of Ferris Wheels in the Middle East.
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter Two, Early United States Ferris Wheels, 1870s-1900s (Legalbox 28, Folder 4)
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter Four, Expositions and Ferris Wheels (Legalbox 29, Folder 1)
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter Five, Amusement Parks, Carousels, Ferris Wheels, 1910s-1980s (Legalbox 29, Folder 2)
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter Six, Astro Wheels to Zippers, 1920s-1990s (Legalbox 29, Folder 3)
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Chapter Seven, For Ferris Wheel Buffs and All Who Love Amusement Rides, 1870s and 1980s (Legalbox 29, Folder 4)
    - Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History by Norman D. Anderson, Ferris Wheel Illustrations, 1800's-1990's (Legalbox 28, Folder 5)
      Includes a variety of Ferris Wheel images, as well as images with captions from Dr. Anderson's Ferris Wheels: An Illustrated History.
    - Ferris Wheel Image Collection, primarily related to the Columbian Exposition in Chicago, 1890s-1910s (Legalbox 29, Folder 5)
      This material may or may not have been used in Anderson's text Ferris Wheels: An Ilustrated History. However, these images did not appear related to the other publication images in this grouping.
- Artifactual Material & Other Materials
  This series of Ephemera contains material that Anderson included in the final boxes of the collection. While the material is varied, it contains souvenir maps, photocopies, and a very interesting collection from Dahlinger's materials featuring antique photographs and early twentieth-century correspondence from the Eli Bridge Company.
  - "A BIG Wheel" Article on Norman D. Anderson and his Ferris Wheel Research, 1980s-1990s (Legalbox 30, Folder 6)
  - Amusement Business, Billboard Advertising, 75th Anniversary Souvenir Issue, 12/31/1969 (Legalbox 29, Folder 15)
  - Civil Engineering, The Magazine of the American Society of Civil Engineers, 10/01/2009-10/31/2009 (Legalbox 30, Folder 3)
  - Collection of Various Ferris Wheel Photographs and Images, 1900s-2000s (Legalbox 30, Folder 1)
    These photographs were grouped together in a box, though their relationship is unspecified.
  - Decorative Carnival-Themed Sign with Ferris Wheel, undated (Legalbox 30, Folder 8)
  - Farm Machinery Advertisement; Strobel, Ohio, 1903 (Legalbox 30, Folder 4)
  - Ferris Wheels From Around the World Calendar, Richard Weingardt Consultants, Inc., 2009 (Legalbox 29, Folder 6)
  - Illustrated Guide to the World's Fair and Chicago, 1892-1893 (Legalbox 29, Folder 12)
  - Souvenir Book from the Pan-American Exposition in Buffalo and Nigara, 1901 (Legalbox 29, Folder 7)
  - Li'l Abner Cream of Wheat Ferris Wheel Cartoon, 1943 (Legalbox 30, Folder 5)
  - Official Souvenir Map, New York World's Fair, 1965 (Legalbox 29, Folder 8)
  - Official World's Fair in Pictures: A Century of Progress Exhibition, 1933 (Flatbox 34)
  - Page from McDonald Brothers Company Catalog, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1910 (Legalbox 29, Folder 11)
    This page is from a paper company's mail-order catalog. It includes information on postcards and, interestingly, a "Ferris Wheel Post Card Display Rack."
  - The Pittsburgh Press, Sunday Magazine, 7/27/1986 (Legalbox 30, Folder 2)
  - Photocopy of "Ferris Wheel March" Cover, undated (Legalbox 30, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Ferris Wheel from Mrs. Violet Schrader, circa 1900 (Legalbox 29, Folder 16)
    This photograph is labeled CEC- 191 on the original packaging material. This refers to Columbian Exposition Chicago, Item 191. Though Dr. Anderson does not use this number in his supplementary list of Columbian Expositon materials [included in Box 6], this piece corresponds with those materials.
  - Revue, the Official Publication of the Outdoor Amusement Business Association, 1993 (Legalbox 29, Folder 14)
  - Ride and Zoo Voucher from Castle Creek Zoo Farm and Kiddieland, New York, undated (Legalbox 29, Folder 9)
  - Small Collection of Various Images, Including Advertorial from Chance Manufacturing Industries, circa 1980s-2000s (Legalbox 29, Folder 10)
  - "The Old Ferris Wheel" Sheet Music, Featured by Bing Crosby, 1947 (Legalbox 29, Folder 13)
  - Why the School Marm Walked Into the Sea (Legalbox 18, Folder 11)